be a part or even be the center of our medical team? What if Musu could help us bring health care from clinics in cities to the doorsteps of her neighbors? Musu was 48 when I met her. And despite her amazing talent and grit, she hadn't had a paying job in 30 years. So what if technology could support her? What if we could invest in her with real training, equip her with real medicines, and have her have a real job? Well, in 2007, I was trying to answer these questions, and my wife and I were getting married that year. We asked our relatives to forgo the wedding registry gifts and instead donate some money so we could have some start-up money to launch a nonprofit. I promise you, I'm a lot more romantic than that. (Laughter) We ended up raising $6,000, teamed up with some Liberians and Americans and launched a nonprofit called Last Mile Health. Our goal is to bring a health worker within reach of everyone, everywhere. We designed a three-step process -- train, equip and pay -- to invest more deeply in volunteers like Musu to become paraprofessionals, to become community health workers. First we trained Musu to prevent, diagnose and treat the top 10 diseases afflicting families in her village. A nurse supervisor visited her every month to coach her. We equipped her with modern medical technology, like this $1 malaria rapid test, and put it in a backpack full of medicines like this to treat infections like pneumonia, and crucially, a smartphone, to help her track and report on epidemics. Last, we recognized the dignity in Musu's work. With the Liberian government, we created a contract, paid her and gave her the chance to have a real job. And she's amazing. Musu has learned over 30 medical skills, from screening children for malnutrition, to assessing the cause of a child's cough with a smartphone, to supporting people with HIV and providing follow-up care to patients who've lost their limbs. Working as part of our team, working as paraprofessionals, community health workers can help ensure that a lot of what your family doctor would do reaches the places that most family doctors could never go. One of my favorite things to do is to care for patients with community health workers. So last year I was visiting A.B., and like Musu, A.B. had had a chance to go to school. He was in middle school, in the eighth grade, when his parents died. He became an orphan and had to drop out. Last year, we hired and trained A.B. as a community health worker. And while he was making door to door house calls, he met this young boy named Prince, whose mother had had trouble breastfeeding him, and by the age of six months, Prince had started to waste away. A.B. had just been taught how to use this color-coded measuring tape that wraps around the upper arm of a child to diagnose malnutrition. A.B. noticed that Prince was in the red zone, which meant he had to be hospitalized. So A.B. took Prince and his mother to the river, got in a canoe and paddled for four hours to get to the hospital. Later, after Prince was discharged, A.B. taught mom how to feed baby a food supplement. A few months ago, A.B. took me to visit Prince, and he's a chubby little guy. (Laughter) He's meeting his milestones, he's pulled himself up to a stand, and is even starting to say a few words. I'm so inspired by these community health workers. I often ask them why they do what they do, and when I asked A.B., he said, "Doc, since I dropped out of school, this is the first time I'm having a chance to hold a pen to write. My brain is getting fresh." The stories of A.B. and Musu have taught me something fundamental about being human. Our will to serve others can actually help us transform our own conditions. I was so moved by how powerful the will to serve our neighbors can be a few years ago, when we faced a global catastrophe. In December 2013, something happened in the rainforests across the border from us in Guinea. A toddler named Emile fell sick with vomiting, fever and diarrhea. He lived in an area where the roads were sparse and there had been massive shortages of health workers. Emile died, and a few weeks later his sister died, and a few weeks later his mother died. And this disease would spread from one community to another. And it wasn't until three months later that the world recognized this as Ebola. When every minute counted, we had already lost months, and by then the virus had spread like wildfire all across West Africa, and eventually to other parts of the world. Businesses shut down, airlines started canceling routes. At the height of the crisis, when we were told that 1.4 million people could be infected, when we were told that most of them would die, when we had nearly lost all hope, I remember standing with a group of health workers in the rainforest where an outbreak had just happened. We were helping train and equip them to put on the masks, the gloves and the gowns that they needed to keep themselves safe from the virus while they were serving their patients. I remember the fear in their eyes. And I remember staying up at night, terrified if I'd made the right call to keep them in the field. When Ebola threatened to bring humanity to its knees, Liberia's community health workers didn't surrender to fear. They did what they had always done: they answered the call to serve their neighbors. Community members across Liberia learned the symptoms of Ebola, teamed up with nurses and doctors to go door-to-door to find the sick and get them into care. They tracked thousands of people who had been exposed to the virus and helped break the chain of transmission. Some ten thousand community health workers risked their own lives to help hunt down this virus and stop it in its tracks. (Applause) Today, Ebola has come under control in West Africa, and we've learned a few things. We've learned that blind spots in rural health care can lead to hot spots of disease, and that places all of us at greater risk. We've learned that the most efficient emergency system is actually an everyday system, and that system has to reach all communities, including rural communities like Emile's. And most of all, we've learned from the courage of Liberia's community health workers that we as people are not defined by the conditions we face, no matter how hopeless they seem. We're defined by how we respond to them. For the past 15 years, I've seen the power of this idea to transform everyday citizens into community health workers -- into everyday heroes. And I've seen it play out everywhere, from the forest communities of West Africa, to the rural fishing villages of Alaska. It's true, these community health workers aren't doing neurosurgery, but they're making it possible to bring health care within reach of everyone everywhere. So now what? Well, we know that there are still millions of people dying from preventable causes in rural communities around the world. And we know that the great majority of these deaths are happening in these 75 blue-shaded countries. What we also know is that if we trained an army of community health workers to learn even just 30 lifesaving skills, we could save the lives of nearly 30 million people by 2030. Thirty services could save 30 million lives by 2030. That's not just a blueprint -- we're proving this can be done. In Liberia, the Liberian government is training thousands of workers like A.B. and Musu after Ebola, to bring health care to every child and family in the country. And we've been honored to work with them, and are now teaming up with a number of organizations that are working across other countries to try to help them do the same thing. If we could help these countries scale, we could save millions of lives, and at the same time, we could create millions of jobs. We simply can't do that, though, without technology. People are worried that technology is going to steal our jobs, but when it comes to community health workers, technology has actually been vital for creating jobs. Without technology -- without this smartphone, without this rapid test -- it would have been impossible for us to be able to employ A.B. and Musu. And I think it's time for technology to help us train, to help us train people faster and better than ever before. As a doctor, I use technology to stay up-to-date and keep certified. I use smartphones, I use apps, I use online courses. But when A.B. wants to learn, he's got to jump back in that canoe and get to the training center. And when Musu shows up for training, her instructors are stuck using flip charts and markers. Why shouldn't they have the same access to learn as I do? If we truly want community health workers to master those lifesaving skills and even more, we've got to change this old-school model of education. Tech can truly be a game changer here. I've been in awe of the digital education revolution that the likes of Khan Academy and edX have been leading. And I've been thinking that it's time; it's time for a collision between the digital education revolution and the community health revolution. And so, this brings me to my TED Prize wish. I wish -- I wish that you would help us recruit the largest army of community health workers the world has ever known by creating the Community Health Academy, a global platform to train, connect and empower. (Applause) Thank you. Here's the idea: we'll create and curate the best in digital education resources. We will bring those to community health workers around the world, including A.B. and Musu. They'll get video lessons on giving kids vaccines and have online courses on spotting the next outbreak, so they're not stuck using flip charts. We'll help these countries accredit these workers, so that they're not stuck remaining an under-recognized, undervalued group, but become a renowned, empowered profession, just like nurses and doctors. And we'll create a network of companies and entrepreneurs who've created innovations that can save lives and help them connect to workers like Musu, so she can help better serve her community. And we'll work tirelessly to persuade governments to make community health workers a cornerstone of their health care plans. We plan to test and prototype the academy in Liberia and a few other partner countries, and then we plan to take it global, including to rural North America. With the power of this platform, we believe countries can be more persuaded that a health care revolution really is possible. My dream is that this academy will contribute to the training of hundreds of thousands of community members to help bring health care to their neighbors -- the hundreds of millions of them that live in the world's most remote communities, from the forest communities of West Africa, to the fishing villages of rural Alaska; from the hilltops of Appalachia, to the mountains of Afghanistan. If this vision is aligned with yours, head to communityhealthacademy.org, and join this revolution. Let us know if you or your organization or someone you know could help us as we try to build this academy over the next year. Now, as I look out into this room, I realize that our journeys are not self-made; they're shaped by others. And there have been so many here that have been part of this cause. We're so honored to be part of this community, and a community that's willing to take on a cause as audacious as this one, so I wanted to offer, as I end, a reflection. I think a lot more about what my father taught me. These days, I too have become a dad. I have two sons, and my wife and I just learned that she's pregnant with our third child. (Applause) Thank you. I was recently caring for a woman in Liberia who, like my wife, was in her third pregnancy. But unlike my wife, had had no prenatal care with her first two babies. She lived in an isolated community in the forest that had gone for 100 years without any health care until ... until last year when a nurse trained her neighbors to become community health workers. So here I was, seeing this patient who was in her second trimester, and I pulled out the ultrasound to check on the baby, and she started telling us stories about her first two kids, and I had the ultrasound probe on her belly, and she just stopped mid-sentence. She turned to me and she said, "Doc, what's that sound?" It was the first time she'd ever heard her baby's heartbeat. And her eyes lit up in the same way my wife's eyes and my own eyes lit up when we heard our baby's heartbeat. For all of human history, illness has been universal and access to care has not. But as a wise man once told me: no condition is permanent. It's time. It's time for us to go as far as it takes to change this condition together. Thank you. (Applause)
formasen parte o incluso fuesen el núcleo de nuestro equipo médico? ¿Y si Musu nos ayudase a llevar la asistencia médica de las clínicas a las puertas de sus vecinos? Musu tenía 48 años cuando la conocí. Y pese a su increíble talento y ambición no había tenido un trabajo remunerado en los últimos 30 años. ¿Y si la tecnología pudiese apoyarla? ¿Y si pudiésemos invertir en ella con una formación real, dotarla de medicamentos reales, y que tenga un trabajo de verdad? En 2007 estaba intentando responder a estas preguntas, y ese año mi mujer y yo nos casamos. Pedimos a nuestros familiares que se olvidasen de los regalos de boda y en su lugar donasen algo de dinero para poder lanzar una organización sin ánimo de lucro. Se los prometo, soy mucho más romántico que eso. (Risas) Finalmente reunimos USD 6000, entre liberianos y estadounidenses y lanzamos una organización, llamada "Last Mile Health". El objetivo es tener un trabajador de la salud al alcance de todos, en cualquier lugar. Diseñamos un proceso de tres pasos: Formar, equipar y pagar, para invertir profundamente en que voluntarios como Musu se conviertan en paraprofesionales, en personal de salud de la comunidad. Primero formamos a Musu para prevenir, diagnosticar y tratar las 10 enfermedades más comunes que afectan a familias de su aldea. Un enfermero supervisor la visitaba cada mes para formarla. La equipamos con tecnología médica moderna como este test rápido para la malaria de 1 dólar. Lo pusimos en una mochila como esta, llena de medicamentos para tratar infecciones como la neumonía, y algo crucial, un teléfono inteligente, para ayudarla a estar al tanto e informar de epidemias. Por último, reconocimos la dignidad del trabajo de Musu. Creamos un contrato con el gobierno de Liberia, le pagamos, le dimos la oportunidad de tener un trabajo real. Y es increíble. Musu ha aprendido más de 30 habilidades médicas. Desde examinar a niños en búsqueda de malnutrición, a evaluar la tos de un niño con su teléfono inteligente, hasta hacer un seguimiento de personas con VIH y proveer cuidados periódicos a pacientes que perdieron sus extremidades. Trabajando en nuestro equipo, como paraprofesionales, los trabajadores de salud pueden garantizar que gran parte de lo que haría tu médico de familia llegue a lugares donde la mayoría de los médicos de familia no pueden ir. Una de las cosas que más me gusta es atender a pacientes con trabajadores de la salud. El año pasado estaba visitando a A.B., y al igual que Musu, A.B. había tenido la oportunidad de ir al colegio. Estaba en la secundaria, en octavo curso, cuando sus padres murieron. Se quedó huérfano y tuvo que dejar. El año pasado contratamos y formamos a A.B. como asistente de salud. Atendiendo puerta a puerta conoció a un niño pequeño llamado Prince, cuya madre había tenido problemas al darle el pecho, y cuando tenía seis meses, Prince empezó a consumirse. A.B. había aprendido a usar una cinta con un código de colores que se pone alrededor del brazo del niño para diagnosticar malnutrición. A.B. vio que Prince estaba en la zona roja, por lo que debía ser hospitalizado. Entonces A.B. llevó a Prince y a su madre al río, se subieron en la canoa y remó 4 horas hasta llegar al hospital. Más tarde, después de dar el alta a Prince A.B. enseñó a su madre cómo darle un suplemento alimenticio. Hace unos meses, A.B. me llevó a conocer a Price, este pequeño gordinflón de aquí. (Risas) Está cumpliendo sus metas, se levanta por sí mismo, y está empezando a decir algunas palabras. Esta comunidad me inspira mucho. A menudo les pregunto por qué hacen lo que hacen, y cuando le pregunté a A.B., me dijo: "Doc, desde que dejé la escuela, es la primera vez que tengo la oportunidad de tomar un bolígrafo. Mi cerebro está rejuveneciendo". Las historias de A.B. y Musu me han enseñado algo fundamental sobre ser humano. Nuestro deseo de ayudar a los demás puede ayudarnos a transformar nuestra propias situaciones. Hace unos años me conmovió cuán poderoso puede ser el deseo de ayudar a nuestros vecinos. Hace unos años, cuando nos enfrentamos a una catástrofe global. En diciembre de 2013, ocurrió algo en la selva a lo largo de la frontera de Guinea. Una criaturita llamada Emile enfermó con vómitos, fiebre y diarrea. Él vivía en un área donde las carreteras escaseaban y había gran escasez de asistentes de salud en la comunidad. Emile murió, y en pocas semanas murió su hermana, semanas después murió su madre. Esta enfermedad se esparcía de una comunidad a otra. No fue hasta tres meses después que el mundo lo reconoció como Ébola. Con cada minuto perdimos meses, y el virus se esparcía como la pólvora en toda África occidental, y por último, en otras partes del mundo. Las empresas cerraron, las aerolíneas empezaron a cancelar rutas. A estas alturas de la crisis, nos dijeron que podrían estar infectadas 1,4 millones de personas cuando nos dijeron que la mayoría de ellos se moriría, cuando habíamos perdido casi toda esperanza, recuerdo estar con un grupo de asistentes de salud en la selva donde acababa de producirse un brote. Estábamos formándoles para que se pusieran las máscaras, los guantes y el traje que necesitaban para mantenerse a salvo del virus mientras atendían a sus pacientes. Recuerdo el miedo en sus ojos. Y recuerdo no pegar ojo de noche, aterrado pensando en si hice lo correcto dejándoles en las calles. Cuando el Ébola amenazó con poner a la humanidad de rodillas, los trabajadores de salud de Liberia no se rindieron ante el miedo. Hicieron lo que siempre han hecho: responder a la llamada para atender a sus vecinos. Trabajadores de toda Liberia estudiaron los síntomas del Ébola, hicieron equipo con enfermeros y médicos para ir puerta por puerta a buscar enfermos y tratarlos. Seguían a miles de personas que habían sido expuestas al virus y ayudaron a romper la cadena de transmisión. Una comunidad de 10 000 trabajadores de la salud arriesgó sus vidas para ayudar a atrapar el virus y detenerlo en el camino. (Aplausos) Hoy, el Ébola está bajo control en África occidental, y hemos aprendido varias cosas. Que los puntos ciegos en la asistencia sanitaria rural pueden convertirse en puntos de contagio, y en esos lugares todos corremos grandes riesgos. Que el sistema de emergencia más eficiente es un sistema del día a día, y ese sistema tiene que llegar a todas las comunidades, incluyendo comunidades rurales como la de Emile. Y sobre todo, hemos aprendido de la valentía de los trabajadores de salud de Liberia, que no nos definen las situaciones a las que nos enfrentamos, sin importar lo desesperanzadoras que parezcan. Nos define cómo respondemos a ellas. Los últimos 15 años, he visto el poder de esta idea de transformar los ciudadanos de a pie en trabajadores de salud... en héroes del día a día. Y funciona en todos lados, desde los bosques de África occidental, hasta los pueblos pesqueros de Alaska. Es cierto, estos trabajadores de la salud no hacen neurocirugías, pero hacen que sea posible llevar la asistencia médica al alcance de todos, en todos lados. ¿Y ahora qué? Sabemos que todavía mueren millones de personas de enfermedades prevenibles en comunidades rurales de todo el mundo. Y sabemos que la gran mayoría de estas muertes ocurren en estos 75 países señalados en azul. También sabemos que si entrenamos un ejército de trabajadores de la salud para aprender tan solo 30 destrezas para salvar vidas, podríamos salvar la vida de casi 30 millones de personas para 2030. Treinta destrezas podrían salvar 30 millones de vidas para el 2030. No es solo un plan... estamos demostrando que se puede hacer. En Liberia, el gobierno está formando miles de trabajadores como A.B. y Musu tras el Ébola, para llevar la asistencia médica a cada niño y familia del país. Estamos encantados de trabajar con ellos y estamos uniendo fuerzas con varias organizaciones que trabajan en otros países para ayudarles a hacer lo mismo. Si podemos ayudar a esos países a hacerlo, podríamos salvar millones de vidas y, al mismo tiempo, podríamos crear millones de empleos. Sin embargo, sencillamente no se puede hacer sin tecnología. Nos preocupa que la tecnología nos robe nuestros empleos, pero cuando se habla de trabajadores de la salud, la tecnología ha sido vital para crear nuevos empleos. Sin tecnología... sin este teléfono inteligente, sin este test rápido... nos hubiera sido imposible contratar a A.B. y a Musu. Creo que es hora de que la tecnología nos ayude a formar, nos ayude a formar personas más rápidamente y mejor que nunca antes. Como médico, uso la tecnología para estar al día. Teléfonos inteligentes, aplicaciones, cursos en línea... Pero cuando A.B. quiere aprender, tiene que subirse a esa canoa e ir al centro de formación. Y cuando Musu viene a clase, sus profesores están estancados usando rotafolio y marcadores. ¿Por qué no deberían tener el mismo acceso al aprendizaje que yo? Si realmente queremos que los asistentes de la salud dominen estas e incluso más habilidades para salvar vidas tenemos que cambiar este modelo de educación anticuado. La tecnología puede cambiar las reglas del juego. Me asombra la revolución digital en la educación tal y como la han liderado Khan Academy y edX. Y creo que ya es hora... es hora de confrontar la revolución digital educativa y la revolución de la salud comunitaria. Esto me lleva a mi deseo del Premio TED. Deseo... que nos ayuden a reclutar el mayor ejército de trabajadores de salud que el mundo ha conocido creando la Community Health Academy, una plataforma global para formar, conectar y empoderar. (Aplausos) Gracias. Esta es la idea: crearemos y seleccionaremos los mejores recursos digitales para la educación. Se los daremos a la comunidad de trabajadores de salud del mundo, incluyendo a A.B. y a Musu. Tendrán lecciones en vídeo de cómo vacunar niños y cursos on-line para detectar el próximo brote, así no usarán rotafolios. Ayudaremos a estos países a destacar a estos trabajadores, para que sean visibles, que no sean infravalorados, sino que tengan una profesión de renombre, empoderada, igual que los enfermeros y médicos. Y crearemos una red de empresas y emprendedores cuyas innovaciones puedan salvar vidas y les ayudaremos a conectar con trabajadores como Musu, para que puedan atender mejor a su comunidad. Y trabajaremos sin descanso para persuadir a los gobiernos y hacer de estos trabajadores una piedra angular del sistema de salud. Queremos probar y prototipar esta academia en Liberia y algunos países colaboradores, y planeamos hacerlo global, incluyendo las áreas rurales del norte de América del Norte Con el poder de esta plataforma, creemos que los países pueden ser persuadidos de que realmente es posible una revolución en la asistencia de salud. Mi sueño es que esta academia contribuya al aprendizaje de cientos de miles de miembros de la comunidad que ayuden a llevar la asistencia sanitaria a sus vecinos... cientos de millones de ellos que viven en las comunidades más remotas del mundo, desde las comunidades boscosas de África occidental, hasta los pueblos pesqueros de la Alaska rural, desde las colinas de los Apalaches, hasta las montañas de Afganistán. Si esta visión se alinea con la de Uds., visiten communityhealthacademy.org y súmense a esta revolución. Queremos saber si Uds. o su organización o alguien que conocen nos puede ayudar mientras intentamos construir esta academia durante el próximo año. Cuando miro a la sala, me doy cuenta de que un camino no se construye solo, sino que otros les dan forma. Hay muchos aquí que han sido parte de esta causa. Estamos honrados de formar parte de esta comunidad, de una comunidad que está dispuesta a tomar una causa tan osada como esta, así que me gustaría, dejarles una reflexión para terminar. Pienso mucho más en lo que me enseñó mi padre. Hace poco, yo también he sido padre. Tengo dos hijos, y mi mujer y yo acabamos de saber que está embarazada del tercero. (Aplausos) Gracias. Hace poco estaba cuidando a una mujer en Liberia quien, como mi esposa, estaba en su tercer embarazo. Pero, al contrario que mi esposa, no había tenido cuidados prenatales con sus dos primeros bebés. Vivía en una comunidad aislada en un bosque de más de 100 años, sin ninguna asistencia de salud hasta que... hasta que el año pasado un enfermero formó a sus vecinos para que se convirtiesen en trabajadores de salud. Aquí estaba yo, consultando a esta paciente que estaba en su segundo trimestre. Saqué el ultrasonido para controlar la salud del bebé, y ella nos empezó a contar historias de sus dos primeros hijos, yo tenía la sonda en su vientre, y ella se paró en mitad de la frase. Giró hacia mí y dijo: "Doc, ¿qué es ese sonido?" Es la primera vez que había escuchado el latido de su bebé. Y sus ojos se iluminaron del mismo modo que mis ojos y los de mi mujer al escuchar el latido de nuestro hijo. Durante la historia de la humanidad, las enfermedades han sido universales y el acceso a la asistencia no. Un hombre sabio me dijo una vez: ninguna situación es permanente. Ya es hora. Es hora de que vayamos tan lejos como haga falta para cambiar esta situación juntos. Gracias. (Aplausos)